Guide to the Burleith Citizens Association records, 1926-2001 MS2022
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Burleith Citizens Association records
1926-2018
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Burleith Citizens Association (Washington, D.C.)
MS2022
9.5 Linear Feet
Collection includes meeting minutes, correspondence, newsletters, and files with subjects of importance to the residents of Burleith. The collection also includes material about the social activities sponsored by the Burleith Citizens Association such as a neighborhood flea market and art show.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Historical or Biographical Note
The Burleith Citizens Association (BCA) began in 1925 with the adoption of a constitution. The modern history of the Burleith neighborhood began in 1886 when the Huidekoper family came into possession of the Burleith tract. The family built some homes and filled in a large hole at the corner of present day S and 37th streets. Much of the tract remained fields and woods when, in 1922, the Huidekoper family sold the tract to Shannon and Luchs, Inc. Shannon and Luchs, using a consulting architect, designed homes that they marketed to people with moderate income, but above average taste. These homes have an American Colonial architecture style. Many have slate mansard roofs and dormer windows. The homes were priced between $8,950-$13,500. The Burleith neighborhood is located next to Georgetown. The Burleith Citizens Association's articles of incorporation state that the goal of the organization is to "... engage in the promotion of the common good and general welfare of the people of Burleith through activities designated to bring about civic betterment and social improvement." In its efforts to achieve this goal, the BCA participates in many activities and monitors issues important to the community including parking, traffic light installation, noise pollution, and the community's relationship with its neighbor, Georgetown University. These civic activities are complimented by social activities including picnics, an annual flea market, and activities specifically for children including an Easter egg hunt and Halloween party.
Collection Scope and Content
The BCA collection includes meeting minutes, correspondence, newsletters, and files with subjects of importance to the residents of Burleith. The collection also includes material about the social activities sponsored by the BCA such as a neighborhood flea market and art show. In 1973, Burleith celebrated its 50th Anniversary and the material collected for that event constitutes the bulk of the early history of Burleith. This history comes from correspondence and interviews with former residents and the family members of early landowners and promotional materials distributed by Shannon and Luchs, Inc. The Burleith community's major growth began in 1922 when Shannon and Luchs, Inc. purchased a significant portion of the Burleith tract. Shannon and Luchs built most of the 540 homes in Burleith's four-block area. The collection is divided into eleven series based on either the type of material and subject. Within each series the folders are arranged either chronologically or alphabetically by folder title.
Collection Organization
Organized into fourteen series: Activities/Events; Administrative Files; Committees; Correspondence; Graphics; History; Membership; Minutes; Newsletters; Subject files; Ephemera; 2003 Accretion: Correspondence; 2003 Accretion: Minutes; 2003 Accretion: Subject files
Washington (D.C.); Flea markets; Burleith (Washington, D.C.); Anniversaries; Building construction; Washington (D.C.) -- History; Burleith Citizens Association (Washington, D.C.); Shannon & Luchs
- Activities and Events, 1968-1981; MS2022 Series 1; 1.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains information for many of the social events BCA participated in and/or sponsored including the annual dinner, flea market, and picnics. For many of these events the information is brief consisting of only a folder or two. For other events, such as the art show and the Burleith 50th Anniversary celebration, there is more documentation and a researcher may get a more complete history of these events.
  - 50th Anniversary 50 year residents, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
  - 50th Anniversary includes A Short History of Burleith, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 50th Anniversary Proclamation for Burleith Golden Anniversary Day, 1973 May 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Resolution by D.C. City Council honoring Burleith 50th Anniversary, 1973 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual Dinner, 1961-1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual Dinner, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bicentennial, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clean up, Fix up, Paint up, 1956-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Flea Market, 1985-1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Picnic, 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Events Miscellaneous, 1966-1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Art Show: Balloon, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Art Show:Captain's notebook, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Art Show:Chairman's Duties, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Art Show:Chairman's Report, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Art Show:Chairman's Report, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Art Show:Chairman's Report, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Art Show:Chairman's folder, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Art Show:Directories from various art shows and miscellaneous material, 1972-1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Art Show:Financial Summaries, 1968-1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Art Show:Financial Summaries, 1972-1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Art Show:Instructions to artists, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Art Show:Invitations and registration, 1971-1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Art Show:Miscellaneous, 1969-1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Art Show:Photographs, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Art Show:Posters, 1968-1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Art Show:Sales records, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Art Show:Sales tax, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Art Show:Seller's signs, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Art Show:Slides April, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Artists mailing lists and Art Show Registration Cards, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Art show miscellaneous address, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Administrative files, 1972-1989; MS2022 Series 2; 0.25 Linear feet
  The administrative files series is a sample of the operational materials produced by the organization. This material includes Treasurers' reports and by-laws and articles of incorporation. For additional Treasurer's reports researchers should use the Minutes Series.
  - Annual report for foreign and domestic corporations, 1980-1982 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Articles of Incorporation and Bylaws, 1972-1982 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Charity Solicitation licenses, 1973-1977 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Burleith Citizens Association Officers list, 1966-1987 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Report of the Treasurer, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Report of the Treasurer, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Committees, 1961-1989; MS2022 Series 3; 0.25 Linear feet
  The BCA committees represented here are not all the committees within BCA, but do represent a wide range of topics including zoning, service and safety, playground, and Georgetown University.
  - Education Committee, 1971-1979 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Green Lot Garden, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Committee of Georgetown-Community Relations, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Committee on Neighborhood, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Neighborhood Watch, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Neighbors Helping Neighbors, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Noise Committee, 1983-1986 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Playground Committee, 1976-1980 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Public Services and Safety Committee, 1967-1974 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Public Services and Safety Committee, 1974-1985 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Traffic and Parking Committee, 1967-1980 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Traffic and Parking Committee, 1974-1977 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Washington Metropolitan Area Council on Airport Problems, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Zoning and Development (planning) Committee, 1961-1989 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Zoning and Development (planning) Committee, 1974-1983 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Correspondence, 1967-1989; MS2022 Series 4; 0.25 Linear feet
  The correspondence includes outgoing letters that primarily state BCA positions on various issues and perhaps request support and assistance. For example, a letter to the principal of Western High School requesting the use of part of the high school's grounds during the BCA art show. Other series in the collection have correspondence. These two folders arrived with correspondence as their folder designation and therefore Special Collection staff kept them separate. It is possible that some of the topics within these two folders match topics within the Subject Files Series.
  - Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1989 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Graphics, 1973-1976; MS2022 Series 5; 0.25 Linear feet
  The images in this series are a random sampling of various activities such as the children's Halloween party and images of the neighborhood around Burleith including Georgetown University and Western High School. The folders in other series that have images also have documents. The graphics folders have only images.
  - Aerial Georgetown University, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - First Annual Burleith Picnic (negatives), 1973 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Front entrances to houses Reservoir Rd., 38th St., and unidentified, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Halloween party(prints), 1976 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Identified and unidentified people, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Western High School, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
- History, 1887-1972; MS2022 Series 6; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series has materials about the history of the Burleith neighborhood including a brief history written by a resident and promotional material published by Shannon and Luchs, Inc. The material in this series is not a history of BCA. There are also a few blueprints of a Shannon and Luchs house.
  - Abstract of title to Burleith, 1887 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence Jane D. Winer(while Winer was a PhD student at George Washington University), 1970-1972 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence Jane D. Winer, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Interview with Frank Tiernan 50 year resident with material for Skyview of Washington No.20, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous material, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - A Short History of Burleith by Edgar Farr Russell, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - The Story of Burleith by Shannon and Luchs and Burleith Homes Why They Are Different by Shannon and Luchs, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Blueprints: Shannon and Luchs Job #354 Architect W.W. Taylor Jr., undated (Oversize 19, Folder 1)
    These may be a model home
- Membership, 1964-1980; MS2022 Series 7; 1 Linear foot
  The folders in this series are divided by street addresses. Most folders contain a list compiled by the block captains that summarize the addresses for members and the dues paid. The folders also contain the actual membership applications. These applications contain the name of the household members both adult and children and often includes the occupation of the household members and the relationship between the adults in the house.
  - Block Captain membership drive, 1964-1966 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Block Captain membership drive, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Block Captain membership drive, 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Block Captain membership drive, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Block Captain membership drive and final drive reports, 1969-1977 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Membership applications R and S Streets, 1978-1979 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Membership applications T St. and 35th Place, 1978-1979 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Membership applications 37th St., 1978-1979 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Membership applications 38th, 39th Streets, Whitehaven Pkwy, 1978-1979 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Membership applications R St., 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Membership applications S St., 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Membership applications T St., 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Membership applications 35th Place and 35th St., 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Membership applications 37th St., 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Membership applications 38th and 39th Streets, 1979-1980 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Membership applications Reservoir Rd. and Whitehaven Pkwy, 1979-1980 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Membership applications R St., 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Membership applications S St., 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Membership applications T. St., 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Membership applications 35th Place and 35th St., 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Membership applications 37th St., 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Membership applications 38th and 39th Streets, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Membership applications Reservoir Rd. and Whitehaven Pkwy, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Member lists, includes addresses, 1952-1955 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Member lists, 1963-1967 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Member lists, 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Minutes, 1929-1989; MS2022 Series 8; 1.5 Linear feet
  This series includes information for the monthly operations of the organization and often a Treasurer's report.
  - Minutes, 1929-1931 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Minutes, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Minutes, 1932 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Minutes, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Minutes, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Minutes, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Minutes, undated (Box 8)
  - Minutes, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1941 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1942 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1942 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Minutes, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Minutes, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Minutes, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Minutes, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Minutes, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Minutes, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Minutes, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Minutes, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Board meeting, 1953-1954 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Minutes, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Minutes, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Minutes, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Minutes, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Minutes, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Minutes, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Minutes, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Minutes, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Minutes, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Minutes, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Minutes, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Minutes, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Minutes, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Minutes, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Minutes, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Minutes, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Minutes, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Minutes, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Newsletters, 1960-2018; 1960-2015; MS2022 Series 9; 0.5 Linear feet
  The BCA newsletters (name change to the Burleith Bell in October 2004) in this series cover the dates 1960 to 2018.
  - Newsletters, 1960-1967 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Newsletters, 1968-1974 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Newsletters, 1974-1979 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Newsletters, 1979-1983 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Newsletters, 1984-1986 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Newsletters, 1987-1991 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Newsletters, 1992-1994 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Newsletters, 1995-1999 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Newsletters, 1998-2003; Series 9 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Newsletters, Burleith Bell, 2004-2007; Series 9 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Newsletters, Burleith Bell, 2008-2011; Series 9 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Newsletters, Burleith Bell, 2012-2013; Series 9 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Newsletters, Burleith Bell, 2014-2015, 2018; Series 9 (Box 20, Folder 5)
- Subject files, 1939-1989; MS2022 Series 10; 2 Linear feet
  This series includes a wide range of topics from D.C. Federation of Civic Associations to Duke Ellington School and the Hillandale development. All the subjects are important to the BCA and represent issues they worked on or in some way associated with. One of the more interesting subjects in this series is the real estate covenant for Burleith. These include the original covenants and the indentures written to maintain the covenants when after they were set to expire. The material within these subject files may also help researchers understand Burleith's history such as the boundaries maps.
  - Subject Files, 1997-2000 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Advisory Neighborhood Committee Ward 3, 1975-1982 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Brochure A Walk Through Georgetown A Guide to Charming and Historic Georgetown by Kevin Delany, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - City Issues Misc, 1968-1982 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - The Cloisters of Georgetown Development, 1979-1980 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Community Mental Health Center, 1979-1984 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Comprehensive Plan for the National Capital: Proposed Preservation and Historic Features Element 03/17/1983, undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Council of the District of Columbia Owners's Manual, 1985-1986 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - DC Federation of Civic Association, 1961-1983 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - D.C. Federation of Civic Associations, Inc., 1974-1977 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - D.C. Federation of Civic Associations, Inc., 1978-1980 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - D.C. Federation of Civic Associations, Inc., 1981-1987 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - D.C. Jaycee Report on Juvenile Delinquency, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Department of Recreation Annual Reports, 1961-1982 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Duke Ellington School and Stadium, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Fillmore school newspaper articles, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Georgetown University Campus Plan, 1982-2000 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Glover Park, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Gordon Junior High School Yearbook, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Greeting cards, undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Hillandale, 1977-1979 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Hillandale, 1979 June (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Hillandale, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Hillandale January, 1980-1989 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Hillandale newspaper articles, 1970-1989 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Jelleff Boys' and Girls' Club, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Local Publications Origins and Cityscapes, 1974-1979 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Maps Area Survey, 1970 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Maps Original Boundaries, undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Neighborhood Parking Studies Columbia Heights, Adams-Morgan, Georgetown, 1961 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper articles, undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Other organizations various civic associations, undated (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Procedures for the Description of Historic Landmarks and Historic Districts, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Real Estate Covenants, 1939-1942 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Real Estate Indentures B-P, (17th, 35-37th, T, S, R Streets NW), 1941 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Summary of Federal Capital Improvement Program, 1983-1987 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Supercan Garbage Can, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Transportation in DC, 1970-1972 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Ward 3 notebook, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Western High School Course Offerings, 1971-1972 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Whitehaven Community Garden, 1980 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Wisconsin Avenue Corridor Committee, 1975-1977 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - 2320 Wisconsin Avenue A Planned Unit Development (PUD), 1980 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - 2320 Wisconsin Avenue A Planned Unit Development (PUD), 1981 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Wyoming Avenue, 1979-1982 (Box 15, Folder 12)
- Ephemera, undated; MS2022 Series 11; 0.5 Linear feet
  This series includes several trophies from the D.C. Federation of Civic Associations and a Burleith t-shirt.
  - T-shirt, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Trophies, undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Art Show Stamps, undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
- 2003 Accretion: Correspondence, 1998-2000; MS2022 Series 12; 0.25 Linear feet
  The correspondence includes letters that primarily state BCA positions on various issues and perhaps request support and assistance. It is possible that some of the topics within this series match topics within the Subject Files Series
  - Correspondence, 1998-2000 (Box 18, Folder 1)
- 2003 Accretion: Minutes, 1998-2001; MS2022 Series 13; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series includes information for the monthly operations of the organization.
  - Board meeting, 1998-2001 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - General meeting, agendas, and additional docs, 1998-2001 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Regular meetings, undated (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Disks with board, regular, and documents, undated (Box 18, Folder 5)
- 2003 Accretion: Subject files, 1996-2000; MS2022 Series 14; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series includes a wide range of topics from Georgetown University to noise control issues. All the subjects of course were important to the BCA and represent issues they worked on or in some way associated with. The material within these subject files may also help researchers understand Burleith's history.
  - Alcohol Beverage Control issues Georgetown University Block Party, 2000 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Board of Zoning Appeals (BZA) Quarterly meeting, 1999-2000 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Burleith Citizens Association Hospitality Kit, undated (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Emergency Board, 1999 October 20 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Georgetown overlay zoning, undated (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Hardy School flea market BZA, undated (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Noise Control Act, 1996-2000 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Resolutions, undated (Box 18, Folder 14)